Wilson Fielder Jr. papers, Inclusive: 1935-2002, undated, Bulk: 1950-1959, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Wilson Fielder Jr. papers
Inclusive: 1935-2002, undated, Bulk: 1950-1959, undated
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
313
Fielder, Wilson Jr., 1917 - 1950
2 document boxes
The Wilson Fielder Jr. Papers contains correspondence, literary productions, photographs, and personal materials relating to the life and career of Wilson Fielder Jr., a Times reporter who was killed during the Korean War.
Administrative Information
Physical Description
General condition: Good.
Biography/Profile
Wilson Fielder Jr. was born on 1917 July 28th, to Baptist missionaries John Wilson Fielder Sr. and Maudie Ethel Albritton in a hospital in Kaifeng, China. He was the first of five children born to the couple between the years of 1919 and 1932. During those years, the family moved between China and the United States due to the political turmoil in the country. In 1936, Fielder left his family to spend time traveling around Europe. He then moved to Texas, where he began to attend Baylor University to pursue a degree in journalism. By 1939, Fielder had become the editor of the Baylor Lariat, while also working for the Waco-Tribune Herald. Fielder graduated Baylor in 1940 and began to work for the Corpus Christi Caller Times.
Fielder entered the Marine Officer’s Cadet School at Quantico in 1942 to prepare to fight in World War II. Due to his time spent in Asia, he went on to serve in the Pacific with the 5th Marine Division, preparing them for the invasion of Iwo Jima. However, Fielder was then assigned to work in the Chinese language school at UCLA where he met his wife Virginia Lee Berg. Wilson then was hired by the Times in 1949, where he joined their bureau in China, covering the defeat of the Chinese Nationalist Forces.
When the North Korean army invaded the southern half of the peninsula in 1950, Fielder became Time’s correspondent and headed to where fighting was heaviest, the Taejon Front. It was here where the 1st Battalion of the 24th infantry division was attempting to hold the North Korean advance. It also became Fielder’s last known location before he went missing in action during the fighting. It took over two years for Virginia and the Fielders to learn of their son and husband’s death. When Fielder’s body was finally recovered, the 33-year-old man was buried in a graveyard for Westerners outside of Yokohama, Japan, on 1952 March 11th. In Fielder’s memory, a scholarship was established to support students of journalism at Baylor University.
Scope and Content
The Wilson Fielder Jr. papers contains correspondence, literary productions, photographs, and personal materials relating to the life and career of Wilson Fielder Jr., a Times reporter who was killed during the Korean War. The materials in this collection are dated from 1935-2002, with the bulk being from 1950-1959. There are four series in the collection, which are Correspondence, Literary Productions, Photographs, and Personal Materials. Correspondence contains letters written by Wilson and his family, along with letters of sympathy from friends after Fielder's death. Literary Productions contains military records, articles, newspapers, and a diary written by or about Fielder. Photographs contains photographs of Fielder's life and his funeral. Personal Materials contains Fielder's yearbook from officer's school and the ribbons used at his funeral.
Arrangement
Prior to processing, the collection was housed in 1 document box and 1 OVZ box, and arranged in folders with some of the folders labeled according to subject. However, there appeared to have been no original order.
Currently, the collection is arranged in four series: I. Correspondence, II. Literary Productions, III. Photographs, and IV. Personal Materials. They have been placed into new folders and arranged chronologically and alphabetically.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 313. Acquired 2018-11-29
Related Resources
Related references
Darden, Robert. "Wilson Fielder's Last Assignment." Baylor Line Foundation. 2018 November 13. Accessed 2019 March 8.
Jasek, Frank. Soldiers of the Wooden Cross: Military Memorials of Baylor University. Frank Jasek.
Index Terms
Subjects (Organizations)
Baylor University -- History, Military.; United States. Marine Corps.
Places
Korea (North) -- History -- 1948-1994.; United States -- Armed Forces -- Texas -- Biography.
Subjects
Funeral decorations.; Identity cards.; Journalism.; Journalists -- Texas.; Photographs.; Yearbooks.
Genres
Academic theses.; Clippings (Books, newspapers, etc.); Diaries.; Military records.; Newsletters.; Personal correspondence.
- Correspondence, 1935-2002, undated; 1
  Administrative Information
  Physical Description
  General condition: Good.
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains the correspondence relating to Wilson Fielder Jr. The materials include letters to and from his family, wife, and letters of sympathy written to Fielder's family after his death. The materials are dated from 1935 to 2002. The condition of the series is good.
  - Letters, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Letters, 1949-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1986-2002 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Letters of Sympathy (1 of 3), 1950-1952 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Letters of Sympathy (2 of 3), undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Letters of Sympathy (3 of 3), undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Literary Productions, Inclusive: 1935-2001, undated; 2
  This series contains the literary productions of Wilson Fielder Jr., including magazine articles, newsletters, newspaper clippings, military records, the diary of Wilson Fielder Jr., and a thesis written about him. The materials are dated from 1935-2001. The condition of the collection is good.
  - Diary of Wilson Fielder Jr., 1935-1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Military Records, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1945-1965 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Magazines/Newsletters, 1950-2001 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Thesis: “The Price of News: American War Correspondent Causalities” by John Hill Raudy, B.S., 1977 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Times and Newsweek Articles, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Certificates, 1963, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Photographs, Inclusive: undated.; 3
  This series contains photographs relating to Wilson Fielder Jr., including photographs of him as a young man, his time in the military, and of his funeral, gravesite, and memorial plaque on the campus of Baylor University. The condition of the collection is good.
  Index Terms
  Genres
  Photograph album
  - Photographs (1 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Photographs (2 of 2), undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Photographs (3 of 3), undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Personal Materials, 1946-1948, undated; 4
  This series contains the personal materials of Wilson Fielder Jr., which include his identification card for the Marine Corp, his 1948 Marine Corp Officer's School Yearbook, and the ribbons used during his funeral.
  - U.S. Marine Corp I.D., 1946 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Wilson Fielder Jr. Funeral Ribbons, undated (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Reserve Officer’s Class Marine Corp Yearbook, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Medal, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)